<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"  [ ]>
<chapter id="intro">

   <title>Introduction</title>

   <!-- TODO Fix certification if needed -->
   
   <para>
      This guide will walk you through installing and starting up JBoss AS 7. It will then introduce
      key features of the Java EE 6 (Web Profile) programming model, of which JBoss AS 7 is a certified
      implementation.
   </para>   
    
   <para>
      JBoss AS 7 departs from the familiar structure of previous JBoss AS versions, so we recommend 
      all developers follow the steps in <xref linkend="gettingstarted"/> to install and start up the
      application server for the first time. 
   </para>
   
   <para>
      JBoss AS 7 comes with a series of quickstarts aimed to get you up to speed with programming model
      with minimal fuss. We recommend that you work through the examples in the order they are presented
      in this guide, however if you have previous experience with Java EE 6, you may wish to skip some 
      or all of the quickstarts:
   </para>
   
   <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
         <term><xref linkend="helloworld"/></term>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               CDI + Servlet. If you have previously developed applications using technologies such as JSF or Wicket, and
               EJB or Spring, you may wish to skip this quickstart.
            </para>
         </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
         <term><xref linkend="numberguess"/></term>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               CDI + JSF. If you have previously developed applications using technologies such as JSF or Wicket, EJB or
               Spring, and JPA or Hibernate you may wish to skip this quickstart. 
            </para>
         </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
         <term><xref linkend="login"/></term>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               CDI + JSF + EJB + JTA. If you are a Java EE wizard you may wish to skip this quickstart.
            </para>
         </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
         <term><xref linkend="kitchensink"/></term>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               CDI + JSF + EJB + JTA + JAX-RS + JAX-RS + Arquilian. A great starting point for your project.
            </para>
         </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   
</chapter>
