<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"  [ ]>
<chapter id="gettingstarted">

   <title>Getting started with JBoss AS 7</title>

   <para>
      To run the examples with the provided build scripts, you'll need the following:
   </para>

   <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
         <para>the JBoss AS 7 distribution zip, which contains the examples</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>Maven 3, to build and deploy the examples</para>
      </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   
   <para>
      Follow <link linkend="http://maven.apache.org/download.html">the offical Maven installation guide</link>
      if you don't already have Maven 3 installed. You can check which version of Maven you have installed (if any) by 
      running <code>mvn --version</code>. If you see a version newer than 3.0.0, you are ready to go.
   </para>
   
   <para>
      You can also deploy the examples using your favourite IDE. We provide instructions for using Eclipse
      only.
   </para>

   <para>
      Now, download JBoss AS <link linkend="TODO">from the JBoss AS 7 page</link>.
   </para>
   
   <note>
      <para>
         JBoss AS 7 offers the ability to manage multiple AS instances from a single control point. A collection
         of such servers are referred to as members of a "domain", with a single Domain Controller process acting
         as the management control point. Domains can span multiple physical (or virtual) machines, with all AS instances
         on a given host under the control of a Host Controller process. The Host Controllers interact with the Domain Controller
         to control the lifecycle of the AS instances running on that host and to assist the Domain Controller in managing them.
      </para>
      
      <para>
         JBoss AS 7 also offers a standalone mode, which is perfect for a single server. We use this throughout the quickstart
         examples. 
      </para>
   </note>
   
   <section id="install.unix">
      
      <title>Installing and starting JBoss AS 7 on Linux, Unix or Mac OS X</title>
      
      <para>
         First, we need to choose a location for JBoss AS to live. By default, JBoss AS 7 will be extracted
         into <code>jboss-7.x.x.x</code> (where 7.x.x.x matches the version you downloaded):
      </para>
         
      <programlisting>unzip jboss-7.x.x.x.zip</programlisting>
      
      <para>
         Now, let's start JBoss AS 7 in standalone mode:
      </para>
      
      <programlisting>jboss-7.x.x.x/bin/standalone.sh</programlisting>
      
      <note>
         <para>
            If you want to stop JBoss AS, simply press <code>Crtl-C</code> whilst the terminal has focus.
         </para>
      </note>
      
      <para>
         That's it, JBoss AS 7 is installed and running! Visit <ulink url="http://localhost:8080/">http://localhost:8080/</ulink>
         to check the server has started properly.
      </para>
      
      <note>
         <para>
            You can find the server log for standalone instances in 
            <code>jboss-7.x.x.x/standalone/log/server.log</code>. The Getting Started Guide covers more on configuring
            logging.
         </para>
      </note>
   </section>
   
   <section id="install.windows">
      <title>Installing and starting JBoss AS on Windows</title>
      
      <para>
         First, we need to choose a location for JBoss AS to live. By default, JBoss AS 7 will be extracted
         into <code>jboss-7.x.x.x</code> (where 7.x.x.x matches the version you downloaded). Unzip JBoss AS
         using your tool of choice.
      </para>
      
      <para>
         Finally, let's start JBoss AS 7 in standalone mode. Locate your JBoss AS installation and run
         <code>standalone.bat</code> located in <code>bin</code>. 
      </para>
      
      <note>
         <para>
            If you want to stop JBoss AS, simply press <code>Crtl-C</code> whilst the terminal has focus.
         </para>
      </note>
      
      <para>
         That's it, JBoss AS 7 is installed and running! Visit <ulink url="http://localhost:8080/">http://localhost:8080/</ulink>
         to check the server has started properly.
      </para>
      
      <note>
         <para>
            You can find the server log for standalone instances in 
            <code>jboss-7.x.x.x/standalone/log/server.log</code>. The Getting Started Guide covers more on configuring
            logging.
         </para>
      </note>

   </section>
   
   <section id="install.eclipse">
      <title>Starting JBoss AS from Eclipse with JBoss Tools</title>
      
      <para>
         You may choose to use Eclipse rather than the command line to run JBoss AS, and to deploy the examples.
         If you don't wish to use Eclipse, you should skip this section.
     </para>
      
      <note>
         <para>
            In order to use JBoss AS 7 from Eclipse, you must first install JBoss AS for your operating system as
            described in <xref linkend="install.unix"/> or <xref linkend="install.windows"/>.
         </para>
      </note>
      
      <para>
         In order use JBoss AS 7 from Eclipse, you'll need Eclipse Indigo (Eclipse 3.7) and JBoss Tools 3.3 M2
         or newer. If you want to run the quickstarts from Eclipse, you will also need m2eclipse. You can find 
         instructions for installing Eclipse, m2eclipse and JBoss Tools <link linkend="TODO">on the JBoss AS site.</link>.
      </para>
      
      <para>
         Having successfully installed and started Eclipse, we need to add our JBoss AS 7 instance to it. First,
         navigate to <code>File -> New -> Other</code>:
      </para>
      
      <mediaobject>
         <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Eclipse_New_Server_1.jpg"
               format="JPEG" />
         </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      
      <para>Now, locate the New Server Wizard:</para>
      
      <mediaobject>
         <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Eclipse_New_Server_2.jpg"
               format="JPEG" />
         </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      
      <para>And choose JBoss AS 7.0:</para>
      
      <mediaobject>
         <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Eclipse_New_Server_3.jpg"
               format="JPEG" />
         </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      
      <para>Hit <code>Next &gt;</code>, and locate the JBoss AS 7 installation by 
      clicking on <code>Browse ...</code>:</para>
      
      <mediaobject>
         <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Eclipse_New_Server_4.jpg"
               format="JPEG" />
         </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      
      <para>Now, choose the JBoss AS 7 installation directory:</para>
      
      <mediaobject>
         <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Eclipse_New_Server_5.jpg"
               format="JPEG" />
         </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      
      <para>Assuming you selected a valid installation, Eclipse should now allow you to hit
      <code>Finish</code>:</para>
      
      <mediaobject>
         <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Eclipse_New_Server_6.jpg"
               format="JPEG" />
         </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      
      <para>
         Now, let's start JBoss AS 7 from Eclipse. If you previously started JBoss AS 7 from the command line,
         you should stop it there first.
      </para>
      
      <para>
         First, we need to make sure the <code>Server</code> tab is on view. Open the 
         <code>Window -> Show View -> Other...</code> dialog:
      </para>
      
      <mediaobject>
         <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Eclipse_Server_Tab_1.jpg"
               format="JPEG" />
         </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      
      <para>
         And select the <code>Server</code> view:
      </para>
      
      <mediaobject>
         <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Eclipse_Server_Tab_2.jpg"
               format="JPEG" />
         </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      
      <para>
         You should see the <code>Server View</code> appear with the JBoss AS 7 server:
      </para>
      
      <mediaobject>
         <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Eclipse_Server_Tab_3.jpg"
               format="JPEG" />
         </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      
      <para>
         Now, we can start the server. Right click on the server in the <code>Server</code> view,
         and select <code>Start</code>:
      </para>
      
      <mediaobject>
         <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Eclipse_Server_Start_1.jpg"
               format="JPEG" />
         </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      
      <note>
         <para>
            If you want to debug your application, you can simply select <code>Debug</code> rather than
            <code>Start</code>. This will start the server in debug mode, and automatically attach the
            Eclipse debugger.
         </para>
      </note>
      
      <para>
         You'll see the server output in the <code>Console</code>:
      </para>
      
      <mediaobject>
         <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Eclipse_Server_Start_2.jpg"
               format="JPEG" />
         </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      
      <para>
         That's it, we now have the server up and running in Eclipse!
         <!-- TODO We'll show you how to deploy your application to JBoss AS 7 from Eclipse in the next
         chapters as we work through the various quickstarts. -->
      </para>
      
   </section>
   
   <section id="import.eclipse">
      <title>Importing the quickstarts into Eclipse</title>
      
      <para>
         In order to import the quickstarts into Eclipse, you will need m2eclipse installed. You can find 
         instructions for installing Eclipse, m2eclipse and JBoss Tools 
         <link linkend="TODO">on the JBoss AS site</link>.
      </para>
      
      <para>
         First, choose <code>File -> Import...</code>: 
      </para>
      
      <mediaobject>
         <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Import_QuickStarts_1.jpg"
               format="JPEG" />
         </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      
      <para>
         Select <code>Existing Maven Projects</code>:
      </para>
      
      <mediaobject>
         <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Import_QuickStarts_2.jpg"
               format="JPEG" />
         </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      
            <para>
         Click on <code>Browse</code>, and navigate to the <code>quickstarts/</code> directory:
      </para>
      
      <mediaobject>
         <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Import_QuickStarts_3.jpg"
               format="JPEG" />
         </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      
      <para>
         Finally, make sure all 4 quickstarts are found and selected, and click <code>Finish</code>:
      </para>
      
      <mediaobject>
         <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Import_QuickStarts_4.jpg"
               format="JPEG" />
         </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      
      <para>
         Eclipse should now successfully import 4 projects:
      </para>
      
      <mediaobject>
         <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Import_QuickStarts_5.jpg"
               format="JPEG" />
         </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>
         It will take a short time to import the projects, as Maven needs to download the project's dependencies
         from remote repositories.
      </para>      
      
   </section>
   
   <section>
      <title>Managing JBoss Application Server</title>
      
      <para>
         Here we will quickly outline how you can access both the command line interface and the web management interface for
         managing JBoss AS. Detailed information for both can be found in the <ulink url="TODO">Getting Started
         Guide for Adminstrators</ulink>.
      </para>
      
      <para>
         When the server is running, the web management interface can be accessed at <ulink url="http://localhost:9090/console">
         http://localhost:9090/console</ulink>. You can use the web management interface to create datasources, manage deployments
         and configure the server.
      </para>
      
      <para>
         JBoss AS also comes with a command line interface. To run it on Linux, Unix or Mac, execute:
      </para>
      
      <programlisting>jboss-7.x.x.x/bin/jboss-admin.sh</programlisting>
      
      <para>
         Or, on Windows:
      </para>
      
      <programlisting>jboss-7.x.x.x/bin/jboss-admin.bat</programlisting>
      
      <para>
         Once started, type <code>connect</code> to connect to the running JBoss AS instance, and <code>help</code>
         to discover the commands available to you.
      </para>
      
   </section>

</chapter>
